Finding Aid for Michigan Interscholastic Forensic Association records
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
- Activities 1943-2006
  - Individual Events
    - Scripts -- Dramatic Interpretation (BCD) 1998/99 (Box 45)
    - Scripts -- Informative Speaking (BCD) 1998/99 (Box 45)
    - Scripts -- Multiple Interpretation (BCD) 1998/99 (Box 45)
    - Scripts -- Prose Open (BCD) 1998/99 (Box 45)
    - Scripts -- Prose 9/10(BCD), 1998/99, 2 folders (Box 45)
    - Scripts -- Oratory Open (BCD) 1998/99 (Box 45)
    - Scripts -- Oratory 9/10(BCD), 1998/99 (Box 45)
    - Scripts -- Sales (BCD) 1998/99 (Box 45)
    - Scripts -- Poetry (BCD) 1998/99 (Box 45)
    - Scripts -- Storytelling (BCD) 1998/99 (Box 45)
    - Scripts -- Duo Interpretation (A) 1999/00 (Box 45)
    - Scripts -- Informative Speaking Open (A) 1999/00 (Box 45)
    - Scripts -- Informative Speaking 9/10(A), 1999/00 (Box 45)
    - Scripts -- Multiple Interpretation (A) 1999/00 (Box 45)
    - Scripts -- Oratory (A) 1999/00 (Box 45)
    - Scripts -- Poetry Open (A) 1999/00 (Box 45)
    - Scripts -- Prose (A) 1999/00 (Box 45)
    - Scripts -- Radio Broadcasting (A) 1999/00 (Box 45)
    - Scripts -- Sales (A) 1999/00 (Box 45)
    - Scripts -- Duo Interpretation (BCD) 1999/00 (Box 45)
    - Scripts -- Dramatic Interpretation (BCD) 1999/00 (Box 45)
    - Scripts -- Informative Speaking Open (BCD) 1999/00 (Box 45)
    - Scripts -- Informative Speaking 9/10(BCD), 1999/00 (Box 45)
    - Scripts -- Oratory (BCD) 1999/00 (Box 45)
    - Scripts -- Storytelling (BCD) 1999/00 (Box 45)
    - Scripts -- Sales (BCD) 1999/00 (Box 45)
    - Scripts -- Informative Speaking (A) 2001 (Box 45)
    - Scripts -- Duo Interpretation 9/10(BCD), 2001 (Box 45)
    - Scripts -- Oratory (BCD) 2001 (Box 45)
    - Scripts -- Poetry (BCD) 2001 (Box 45)
    - Scripts -- Sales (BCD) 2001 (Box 45)
    - State Tournament 1964/65-2000/01, 37 folders (Box 46)
    - State Tournament 2001/02 (Box 47)
    - State Tournament 2002/03, 2 folders (Box 47)
    - State Tournament 2003/04-2005/06, 3 folders (Box 47)
    - Annual Reports on Forensics 1952-1954 (Box 47)
    - Assorted Event Summaries 1943/44-1983/84 (Box 47)
    - At-Large Process 1990/91 (Box 47)
    - At-Large Submissions and Appeals (Box 47)
    - At-Large Selections 1991-2006 (Box 47)
    - Ballot Examples (Box 47)
    - Broadcasting Texts -- Various Events 1996/97-1999/00, 2 folders (Box 47)
    - Committee Personnel 1979/80-2004/05 (Box 47)
    - Correspondence -- Assignment of Schools to District/Regional Contests (Box 47)
    - Correspondence -- Assorted (Box 47)
    - Correspondence -- Awards (Box 47)
    - Correspondence -- Contest Scheduling Issues (Box 47)
    - Correspondence -- Disqualifications/Withdrawals (Box 47)
    - Correspondence -- Facility Requests (Box 47)
    - Correspondence -- Financial Matters (Box 47)
    - Correspondence -- Interpretations of Rules (Box 47)
    - Correspondence -- Judges for Tournaments 1975-2000, 2 folders (Box 47)
    - Correspondence -- Proposals, Suggestions, Modifications (Box 47)
    - Correspondence -- Protests, Complaints, Violations 1968-2005, 3 folders (Box 47)
    - Correspondence -- Requests for Materials (Box 47)
    - Correspondence -- Schematic Issues (Box 47)
    - Correspondence -- School Participation (Box 47)
    - Correspondence -- Scoring Errors/Placement Alterations (Box 47)
    - Correspondence -- State Tournament Chaperoning (Box 47)
    - Correspondence -- State Tournament Participation (Box 47)
    - Correspondence -- Tournament Hosting/Directing (Box 47)
    - Extemporaneous Speaking Topics -- Various Events 1943-2003/04, 2 folders (Box 47)
    - Impromptu Speaking Topics -- Various Events 1970/71-2003/04, 2 folders (Box 47)
    - Submission of Extemporaneous Speaking Topics 1970s-1983 (Box 47)
    - Frequently Asked Questions (Box 48)
    - Invitational Tournaments and Leagues (Box 48)
    - Judge Lists/Judge Certification Procedure, 1949/50-1997 (Box 48)
    - Judge Certification -- Exams (Box 48)
    - Materials for Tournament Directors (Box 48)
    - Multiple Reading Descriptions and Evaluations 1970s (Box 48)
    - Newspaper Articles (Box 48)
    - Press Release Ideas 1984 (Box 48)
    - Reading Lists circa 1960s (Box 48)
    - Scripts (bound volume) (Box 48)
    - Statistical Summaries, Surveys 1974/75-1994/95 (Box 48)
    - Study on Problems in High School Contests in Interpretive Reading 1954 (Box 48)
    - Suggested Sources for High School Readings 1950s (Box 48)
    - Survey of Dramatic Reading in State Forensic Leagues 1957 (Box 48)
    - Upper Peninsula Forensics -- Schedules, Lists, Correspondence, Reports 1958-1997 (Box 48)
    - Interpretation Pentathlon 1967/68-1968/69 (Box 48)
    - Interpretation Pentathlon 1969/70-1970/71 (Box 48)
    - Interpretation Pentathlon 1971/72-1972/73 (Box 48)
    - Interpretation Pentathlon 1973/74-1974/75 (Box 48)
    - Interpretation Pentathlon 1975/76-1976/77 (Box 48)
    - Interpretation Pentathlon 1977/78-2005/06, 28 folders (Box 48)
    - Interpretation Pentathlon -- Budgets/Scholarship Proposal 1967-1976 (Box 48)
    - Interpretation Pentathlon -- Correspondence 1969-1992 (Box 48)
    - Interpretation Pentathlon -- Results Summaries 1975-1984 (Box 48)
    - Interpretation Pentathlon -- Rules, Speaking Topics 1968-1977 (Box 48)
    - Original Interpretation Tournaments 1995/96-1999/00, 5 folders (Box 48)
    - Original Interpretation Tournaments 2001/02-2004/05, 4 folders (Box 48)
- Michigan High School Oratorical Association 1897-1932
  The Michigan High School Oratorical Association series, 1897-1931, is one of the smallest, but represents the oldest materials in the collection. Its materials are from this legacy organization of MIFA, including an accounting book, a scrapbook with minutes from meetings, and assorted loose items in folders.
  - Accounting Ledgers, Invoices, Receipts 1918-1926 (Box 48)
  - Bulletins, Approved Declamations, Constitutions 1926/27-1931/32 (Box 48)
  - Loose Scrapbook Pages 1927-1931 (Box 48)
  - Account Book of Receipts and Disbursements 1903/04-1925/26, bound volume (Box 48)
  - Scrapbook (bound) 1897-1926 (Box 48)
  - Loose Items from 1897-1926 Scrapbook (Box 48)
  - Loose Newspaper Articles from 1897-1926 Scrapbook (Box 48)
- Multimedia 1967-2003
  The Files of Jon Fitzgerald, Executive Director of MIFA series, 1954-2002 (2 linear feet), details programs and projects associated with MIFA. Two significant programs, the Michigan Speech Coaches Association (MSCA) and the Michigan Future Problem Solvers, are well documented with meeting notes, correspondence, practice problems, and conference materials. Additionally, Fitzgerald's records augment existing Michigan Speech Association (MSA) files with early conference records (1974-1979), example panels, and services. Fitzgerald's interest in speech, both at the high school and collegiate levels, are documented through this series with records from the Bureau of School Services and University of Michigan School of Education. Finally, Fitzgerald's records hold a series of pamphlets produced by MIFA-associated organizations, offering insight into collaborations across the field.
  The series Multimedia, 1947-2000, contains a sample of recordings of MIFA-sponsored activities. The materials include various open and cassette formats of audiotapes and videotapes as well as several transcription discs.
  - Debate
    - Class A Debate, undated, 1/2" open reel videotape (Box 49)
    - Class A Debate 1972, 1/2" open reel videotape (Box 49)
    - Upper Peninsula -- Bicentennial Debates undated, (1/4" open reel audiotape (Box 49)
    - Class A Final 1986/87, 60 videotapes VHS (TM) (Box 49)
    - Class B Final 1986/87, 60 min, VHS videotape (Box 49)
    - Class C/D Final 1986/87, 60 min, VHS videotape (Box 49)
    - Class A Final 1993/94, VHS videotape (Box 49)
    - Class B Final 1993/94, VHS videotape (Box 49)
    - Class C/D Final 1993/94, VHS videotape (Box 49)
    - Flint TV-12 Story on State Debate Tournament 1997, VHS videotape (Box 49)
    - John S. Knight Contest 1980/81, audiocassette (Box 49)
    - John S. Knight Contest 1984/85, Beta videotape (Box 49)
    - John S. Knight Contest 1990, VHS videotape (Box 49)
    - John S. Knight Contest 1990/91, audiocassette (Box 49)
    - John S. Knight Contest 1995/96, VHS videotape (Box 49)
  - Drama/Theatre
    - Theatre Finals 1989/90 (audiocassette) (Box 49)
    - "Scotland Road" by Holland High School 1996 Festival, VHS videotape (Box 49)
    - "A Piece of My Heart" by Frankenmuth High School 1996 Festival, VHS videotape (Box 49)
    - "Wit" by Grand Rapids City High and "Machinal" by Holland High 2000 Festival, VHS videotape (Box 49)
    - "Is There Life After High School" by Avondale High and "Translations" by John Glenn High 2000 Festival, VHS videotape (Box 49)
  - Individual Events
    - Broadcasting State Champions 1991/92-1996/97, 40 min, VHS videotape (Box 49)
    - Upper Peninsula Oratory 1993, VHS videotape (Box 49)
    - Finals 1993/94, two VHS videotapes (Box 49)
    - State Champions -- various events 1996/97, VHS videotape (Box 49)
    - State Champions 1998/99, two VHS videotapes (Box 49)
  - Legislative Debate
    - Student Congress 1967, three 1/4" open reel audiotapes (Box 49)
    - Student Congress 1968, three 1/4" open reel audiotapes (Box 49)
    - Student Congress undated, three 1/4" open reel audiotapes (Box 49)
    - Student Congress 1970, four 1/4" open reel audiotapes (Box 49)
    - Student Congress 1971, two 1/4" open reel audiotapes (Box 49)
    - Student Congress 1973 (two 1/4" open reel audiotapes) (Box 49)
    - Student Congress 1974, 1/4" open reel audiotape (Box 49)
    - Student Congress 1975, 1/4" open reel audiotape (Box 49)
    - Student Congress 1988, VHS videotape (Box 49)
  - Debate Finals
    - Class A, East Lansing vs. Groves, MIFA Debate Finals, undated, (VHS videotape) (Box 50)
    - Class A, B, C, D Awards/MIFA-Debate Finals, undated, (VHS videotape) (Box 50)
    - Novice Finals 1984-1985 (VHS videotape) (Box 50)
    - Novice Finals 1985-1986 MIFA (VHS videotape) (Box 50)
    - Debate Awards Ceremony 1986 (VHS videotape) (Box 50)
    - Class A Finals 1986 (VHS videotape) (Box 50)
    - Class B Finals 1986 (VHS videotape) (Box 50)
    - Class C, D Finals 1986 (VHS videotape) (Box 50)
    - Novice Final Round, Affirmative Birmingham Seaholm, Negative Muskegon Mona Shores 1986 (VHS videotape) (Box 50)
    - Class B Final 1986-1987, 60 videotapes VHS (TM) (Box 50)
    - Novice Final Stage Debate 1988-1989 (VHS videotape) (Box 50)
    - Class B State Finals, Final Round Marshal (A) vs. EGR (N)1988-1989 (VHS videotape) (Box 50)
    - Novice State Finals, Final Round Muskegon Mona Shores (A) vs. EGR (N) 1989-1990 (VHS videotape) (Box 50)
    - Class A State Championship Debate, University Liggett (A) vs. Royal Oak Kimball (N) 1990-1991 (VHS videotape) (Box 50)
    - Class B Finals, EGR vs. Divine Child 1990-1991 (VHS videotape) (Box 50)
    - Class C/D State Championship Debate, Detroit Country Day (A) vs. Ithaca (N) 1990-1991 (VHS videotape) (Box 50)
    - Novice Final Tournament, University Liggett vs. East Grand Rapids 1990-1991 (VHS videotape) (Box 50)
    - Class B, State Debate Tournament 1991-1992 (VHS videotape) (Box 50)
    - Class C/D, State Debate Tournament 1991-1992 (VHS videotape) (Box 50)
    - Novice State Finals 1992-1993 (VHS videotape) (Box 50)
    - Class A Final Round, State Debate Tournament 1992-1993 (VHS videotape) (Box 50)
    - Class B Final Round, State Debate Tournament 1992-1993 (VHS videotape) (Box 50)
    - Class C/D Final Round, State Debate Tournament 1992-1993 (VHS videotape) (Box 50)
    - Class A 1994-1995 (VHS videotape) (Box 50)
    - Class B 1994-1995 (VHS videotape) (Box 50)
    - Class C/D 1994-1995 (VHS videotape) (Box 50)
    - Novice Finals, Groves (A) v. DCDS (N) 1994-1995 (VHS videotape) (Box 50)
    - State Debate Finals, Class A 1995-1996 (VHS videotape) (Box 50)
    - State Debate Finals, Class B, Detroit Country Day vs Wayland 1995-1996 (VHS videotape) (Box 50)
    - State Debate Finals, Class C/D 1995-1996 (VHS videotape) (Box 50)
    - Class B State Finals 1997 (VHS videotape) (Box 50)
    - Class C/D Finals, University of Liggett vs. Cass City 1998 (VHS videotape) (Box 50)
    - Class B Debate Finals, Marshal vs. Brother Rice 1999 (VHS videotape) (Box 50)
    - Debate Finals 1999 (VHS videotape) (Box 50)
    - Class A Final 1999-2000 (VHS videotape) (Box 50)
    - Debate Final Class B 1999-2000 (VHS videotape) (Box 50)
    - Debate Final Class C/D 1999-2000, 2 tapes, VHS videotape (Box 50)
    - A Debate Finals 2000-2001 (VHS videotape) (Box 50)
    - B Debate Finals 2000-2001 (VHS videotape) (Box 50)
    - C/D Debate Finals 2000-2001, 2 tapes, VHS videotape (Box 50)
    - Novice Debate Finals, Groves vs. Dow 2002-2003 (VHS videotape) (Box 50)
- Files of Jon Fitzgerald, Executive Director of MIFA 1954-2002
  - Associated Organization Pamphlets 1954-1994 (Box 51)
  - Bureau of School Services
    - 1962-1968 (Box 51)
    - Basis Meetings 1985-1987 (Box 51)
    - Basis Research Agenda 1985 (Box 51)
    - Bureau Meetings 1967-1987 (Box 51)
    - Committee November 17, 1983 (Box 51)
    - High School Classroom Instruction in Speech 1960-1961 (Box 51)
    - Kehoe, Ray, "Impressions," July 1968 (Box 51)
    - Move 1980 (Box 51)
    - A Report on What It is Doing and What It Plans to Do (Box 51)
    - Room Proposal 1985 (Box 51)
    - Self-Sufficiency Bureau Committee 1983 (Box 51)
    - Speech Contests 1950-1960 (Box 51)
  - Debater's Guidebooks 1956-1976 (Box 51)
  - Michigan Association of Speech Coaches, MASC
    - Annual Business Meeting, Kalamazoo 1994 (Box 51)
    - Annual Business Meeting 1995 (Box 51)
    - Annual Business Meeting 1998 (Box 51)
    - Conference, Ypsilanti, Fall 1991 (Box 51)
    - Conference 1992 (Box 51)
    - Conference, Fall 1996 (Box 51)
    - Conference, Fall 1997 (Box 51)
    - Conference, Fall 1998 (Box 51)
    - Conference, Fall 1999 (Box 51)
    - Conference, 75th Anniversary, Fall 2000 (Box 51)
    - Conference, Fall 2001 (Box 51)
    - Constitution and By-Laws 1978-1997 (Box 51)
    - Correspondence, Miscellaneous 1974-1985 (Box 51)
    - Debate Tournament 1973-2002 (Box 51)
    - Executive Council 1990-1998 (Box 51)
    - Hall of Fame 1978-1994 (Box 51)
    - Inter-college Debate Program-Proposal 1985-1986 (Box 51)
    - Listening and Speaking Committee 1977-1991 (Box 51)
    - "M" Forensic Team 1987-1988 (Box 51)
    - Mailings 1998-2002 (Box 51)
    - Meeting Minutes 1974-2001 (Box 51)
    - Membership 1989-1993 (Box 51)
    - Membership Directories 1972-2001 (Box 51)
    - Named Scholarship 2000 (Box 51)
    - State Finals 2001 (Box 51)
    - Youth Poetry Slam 2000 (Box 51)
  - Michigan Future Problem Solvers
    - Brainstormer 1984-1990 (Box 51)
    - Dawn/Gordon Booklet 1984-1985 (Box 51)
    - Elections (Box 51)
    - Evaluation Materials 1986-1989 (Box 51)
    - Executive Board Meeting 1984 (Box 51)
    - Executive Board Meeting 1985 (Box 51)
    - Executive Board Meeting 1986 (Box 51)
    - Executive Board Meeting 1987 (Box 52)
    - Executive Board Meeting 1988 (Box 52)
    - Executive Board Meeting 1988-1989 (Box 52)
    - Executive Board Meeting 1989-1990 (Box 52)
    - Future X 1986 (Box 52)
    - Future X 1987 (Box 52)
    - "Get to Know You Game" (Box 52)
    - Hunger Practice Problem 1986 (Box 52)
    - International Conference 1986 (Box 52)
    - IRS Classification September 29, 1985 (Box 52)
    - Kunze Letter February 1985 (Box 52)
    - Member Mail 1982-1983 (Box 52)
    - October 1984 (Box 52)
    - Organization Materials 1980 (Box 52)
    - Paraphernalia (Box 52)
    - Practice Problems 1985-1986 (Box 52)
    - Resource Manual 1986-1987 (Box 52)
    - Resource Manual 1987-1988 (Box 52)
    - Scenarios (Box 52)
    - State Bowl 1985 (Box 52)
    - State Bowl 1986 (Box 52)
    - State Bowl 1987 (Box 52)
    - State Bowl 1988 (Box 52)
  - Michigan Speech Association, MSA
    - MSA Conference
      - Fall Conference 1974 (Box 52)
      - Spring Conference 1975 (Box 52)
      - Fall Conference 1975 (Box 52)
      - Fall Conference Evaluations 1975 (Box 52)
      - Spring Conference 1976 (Box 52)
      - Fall Conference 1977 (Box 52)
      - Fall Conference 1979 (Box 52)
    - Okey Scholarship 1987 (Box 52)
    - Placement Services 1976 (Box 52)
    - Speech Activities January 10, 1974 (Box 52)
    - Watergate Panel 1974 (Box 52)
  - UM School of Education
    - MI School Band and Orchestra Association 1979-1986 (Box 52)
    - Newspaper Clippings 1982-1983 (Box 52)
    - Speech Department 1964-1965 (Box 52)
    - Task Force/Transition 1983-1984 (Box 52)
- Scrapbooks 1935-1952
  The Scrapbook series, 1935-1952 (1 liner foot), is composed of three scrapbooks that contain mainly newspaper clippings that document activities of the Michigan High School Forensic Association, the forerunner of MIFA.
  - 1935-1946 (Box 53)
  - 1948-1949 (Box 53)
  - 1950-1952 (Box 53)